Women Art Revolution: videotape interviews by Lynn Hershman-Leeson M1639
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Interviews
  - Robert Kushner
    Painter and sculptor Robert Kushner (b. 1949) is one of the few American decorative painters of our era, producing colorful, florally embellished work since 1971. Kushner is also one of the few men who had a key role in the Pattern and Decoration Movement. Originating in New York in the mid-1970s, the movement was one aspect of the reaction against the stark impersonality of Minimal art and also represented a defense of the idea that decorative art is a humanizing influence that should not be regarded as inferior to "fine" art. Many of the artists involved in the movement were women who were interested in exploring how the decorative crafts that have traditionally carried feminine associations could bear renewed, progressive meanings. Notable artists in this group include Joyce Kozloff and Miriam Schapiro. Kushner continues to work in this mode; on the occasion of his twenty-five year retrospective at the New Jersey Center for Visual Arts he noted, "I really believe the public deserves something beautiful."
    - New York, NY; 2006-05-12 (Box 1, Videotape 17A-copy)
      DVCAM (17A-copy), Digital .mov file
  - Suzanne Lacy
    Suzanne Lacy (b. 1945) is an activist and performance artist whose work includes installations, videos and large-scale performances on social themes and urban issues. She often collaborates with other artists to produce works about women's issues. Her first large-scale public work, Three Weeks in May (1977), dramatized the high incidence of rape in Los Angeles. One of her best-known works to date is The Crystal Quilt (Minneapolis, 1987) a performance which included 430 older women and aired live on PBS. She is currently the Chair of Fine Arts at the Otis College of Art and Design in Los Angeles.
    - San Francisco, CA; 1990-05-09 (Box 1, Videotape 18A-18B)
      U-matic (18A, 18B), Digital .mov files (2)
    - Unknown Location; 1990 (Box 1, Videotape 18C)
      U-matic (18C), Digital .mov file
  - Sheila Levrant de Bretteville
    As an artist and arts educator Sheila Levrant de Bretteville (b. 1940) holds a pivotal role in the history of feminist art. She founded the Women's Design Program at the California Institute of the Arts in 1971, co-founded the first independent feminist art school in the United States, the Feminist Studio Workshop in Los Angeles in 1973 (with Judy Chicago and Arlene Raven), and there created the Women's Graphic Center. In 1980 de Bretteville established the Department of Communication Design at the Otis Art Institute, and in 1990 became the first woman to receive tenure at the Yale University School of Art.
    Throughout her career de Bretteville has continually focused on the social implications of design and worked to establish the means by which women artists could collaborate to address and publicize feminist concerns as part of the design process.
    - Los Angeles, CA; 1990 (Box 1, Videotape 7A-7C)
      U-matic (7A, 7B), DVCAM (7C-copy), Digital .mov files (3)
    - New York, NY; 2008-02-15 (Box 1, Videotape 7 D)
      Mini-DV (7D), Digital .mov file
  - Lucy Lippard
    First gaining notoriety as a chronicler of the Postminimal and Conceptual Art movements, Lucy Lippard (b. 1937) has curated and written art criticism since the early 1960s. After publishing the book-length, chronological bibliography Six Years: The Dematerialization of the Art Object in 1973, Lippard narrowed her focus more specifically to art by women. From the Center: Feminist Essays on Women's Art (1976) collects much of her work from the early 1970s; The Pink Glass Swan: Selected Essays on Feminist Art (1995) is a more recent anthology. She has also published monographs on specific artists, such as Judy Chicago and Eva Hesse.
    In her work as a curator, Lippard has pushed the boundaries of the exhibition space, presenting innovatively irregular sculptures in Eccentric Abstraction (1966) and obviating the need for a physical space altogether in 955,000 (1970). In recent years, Lippard has continued to support feminist art and has also turned her attention to issues of climate and place.
    - San Francisco, CA; 1987 (Box 2, Videotape 19B)
      Betacam SP (19B), Digital .mov file
      Paper in Container
      Folded permissory note in container: "This is to confirm I will let Lynn Hershman use my interview on videotape for her tape on women artists and the Feminist Movement - Lucy R. Lippard, 10/18/93"
  - Howardena Pindell
    Howardena Pindell (b. 1943), painter and mixed media artist, curator and educator, is known for the wide variety of techniques and materials used in her artwork. She has created abstract paintings, collages, "video drawings," and "process art." Many of her pieces engage in deconstruction and reconstruction. Her work explores texture, color, structures, and the process of making art; it is often political, addressing the issues of racism, feminism, violence, slavery, and exploitation. Her work is also autobiographical, particularly in the years after a 1979 car accident in which she suffered a concussion and memory loss.
    In 1990 Pindell received the Most Distinguished Body of Work or Performance Award from the College Art Association. Her work is in the collection of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Museum of Modern Art, the Whitney Museum of American Art, the Yale University Art Gallery, the Harvard University Art Museums and the Rhode Island School of Design Museum, among many others.
    - New York, NY; 2006-05-09 (Box 1, Videotape 20A)
      DVCAM (20A), Digital .mov file
  - Yvonne Rainer
    Yvonne Rainer (b. 1934) is a dancer, choreographer, filmmaker, and co-founder, in 1962, of the highly influential Judson Dance Theater in New York. After studying at the Martha Graham School and with Merce Cunningham, she began to choreograph works through which she could challenge traditional notions of dance performance. Most notably in Trio A (first performed in 1968 as part of the larger work The Mind is a Muscle), Rainer utilized a flow of mundane movements to complicate the performer/audience relationship and to draw attention to the body as a functional object—a strategy that finds its parallels in Minimalism. Her work in the 1970s, increasingly film-based, became more oriented toward content and context while still maintaining a focus upon form. Her Film About A Woman Who... (1974) drew attention to the place of women in a male-dominated society. Later films, such as Privilege (1990), have continued this theme, with treatments of menopause and aging, breast cancer, and homosexuality. They repeatedly demonstrate Rainer’s belief in the importance of presenting the female body and the female voice through the critical and self-identifying eye of the female artist.
    - Berkeley, CA; 1990-09-12 (Box 1, Videotape 21A-21B, 21B-copy)
      U-matic (21A, 21B), DVCAM (21B-copy), Digital .mov files (2)
    - San Francisco, CA; 2006-10-24
  - Maura Reilly
    As the Founding Curator of the Elizabeth A. Sackler Center for Feminist Art at the Brooklyn Museum (the permanent home of Judy Chicago's The Dinner Party), Maura Reilly has worked to build the Center into the world's preeminent museum space for the exhibition and interpretation of feminist art. Reilly received her Ph.D. from New York University's Institute of Fine Arts; since then she has taught, curated, and published in the field of feminist and queer theory.
    Reilly has published essays in collected works such as Women Making Art: Women in the Visual, Literary, and Performing Arts Since 1960 (2001) and makes regular contributions to Art in America. Her exhibition catalogs include Global Feminisms: New Directions in Contemporary Art (organized and edited with Linda Nochlin, 2007) and Ghada Amer (2010). A Lifetime Achievement Award from the Women's Caucus for Art is one of several professional honors she has received.
    - New York, NY; 2007-02-06 (Box 1, Videotape 22A)
      Mini-DV (22A), Digital .mov file
  - B. Ruby Rich
    B. Ruby Rich (b. 1949?), a film critic, film festival programmer, cultural theorist, and professor is perhaps best known for her work in feminist film criticism and the creation of the term "New Queer Cinema." In recent years, Rich has written for The Guardian (UK), the SF Bay Guardian, and sf360.org. Previously she was a contributor to Sight and Sound, The Nation, The Village Voice, The New York Times, Cinema Journal, and many other popular and scholarly journals. The author of Chick Flicks: Theories and Memories of the Feminist Film Movement, Rich now teaches in the Social Documentation Program at the University of California, Santa Cruz, where she's currently chair of the Community Studies Department.
    - San Francisco, CA; 2006-10-24 (Box 1, Videotape 23A-23B)
      Mini-DV (23A, 23B), Digital .mov files (2)
  - Faith Ringgold
    Faith Ringgold (b.1930), a writer, painter, sculptor, printmaker and performance artist, is perhaps best known for her painted story quilts which incorporate African American images and narratives. Ringgold's art has redefined black and feminist ideals and is rooted in the strength of African American culture, family, mother-daughter relationships, marriage, sexuality, and female self-expression. Ringgold’s interest in story-telling naturally led to the production of several award-winning children's books with African American themes including Tar Beach, Aunt Harriet's Underground Railroad in the Sky, Dinner at Aunt Connie's House and Bonjour Lonnie. Her web site includes material geared for children and young people. The topic of race is never far away.
    - New York, NY; 1991-09-03 (Box 1, Videotape 24A)
      Hi-8 (24A), Digital .mov file
    - New York, NY; 2006-05-10 (Box 1, Videotape 24B)
      Mini-DV (24B), Digital .mov file
  - Rachel Rosenthal
    Rachel Rosenthal (b. 1926) is a key figure in the development of interdisciplinary performance. Her work incorporates dance, vocals, video, visual effects, and other media as a means to address themes related to animal rights, gender, the environment, and humanity's general place on the planet. Her current dance ensemble, The Rachel Rosenthal Company, is both a traveling performance group and a method of instruction (utilizing her "Doing by Doing" technique) and outreach.
    Rosenthal has spent much of her career in Los Angeles, a city that, she felt upon moving there, lacked much of the restrictive—and masculine—intensity that New York projected. In 1956 she founded the Instant Theatre, a decade-long experiment in teaching and innovative, improvisational performance. In the early years of the feminist art movement in L.A., Rosenthal began collaborating with fellow artists such as Miriam Schapiro and Judy Chicago and helped to found Womanspace Gallery in 1972. Her realization, by way of these collaborations, that her personal experiences—both psychological and physical—held meaning for others has affected her artwork ever since. Rosenthal's performance Charm (1977), for example, was an interpretation of her childhood experiences with deprivation (illustrated by the intimidating figure of her governess) and excess (symbolized by an abundance of pastries and cakes). In The Death Show (1978), she explored the theme of death and its constant presence. Rachel's Brain (1987) was a costumed musing on human excess and nature's regrettable decline into abstraction, related through Rosenthal's unmistakable stage persona.
    In recent years, Rosenthal has moved away from performing herself, concentrating instead upon painting, artists' books, and artistic direction. Over the years she has received awards from the City of Los Angeles, the College Art Association, the Women's Caucus, and many other organizations. She has been included in numerous group shows, including Los Angeles 1955-1985 at the Pompidou Center (2006); many of her works, interviews, and reviews are collected in Moira Roth's monograph Rachel Rosenthal (1997).
    - Los Angeles, CA; 1990-07-27 (Box 1, Videotape 25A, Box 2, Videotape 25B, 25C)
      Hi-8 (25A), U-matic (25B, 25C)
    - Unknown Location; 1992-10-03 (Box 2, Videotape 25D)
      U-matic (25D), Digital .mov file
  - Martha Rosler
    Martha Rosler (b. 1943) is a performance artist, video artist, and photographer whose practice has focused upon issues of politics, class, and gender. Her series Bringing the War Home, begun in 1967, was a set of photomontages that juxtaposed suburban interiors with photographs from the war in Vietnam; it was an early example of the activist content with which she imbued her primarily Conceptual work. The Bowery in two inadequate descriptive systems (1974-75), a spiralbound photobook containing images of the decrepit street placed opposite words indicative of drunken homelessness, was a career-defining work. After it came works of a more explicitly feminist bent: the six-minute video Semiotics of the Kitchen (1975), which drew attention to women’s prescribed domestic roles, and Vital Statistics of a Citizen, Simply Obtained (1977), a video documenting a woman's reduction to her basic physical measurements. Since the 1980s she has returned her focus to more general concepts of social justice: housing, pollution, labor, globalization.
    Rosler is also a critic, and her writing has often intersected with her own creative interests. She has explored the issues surrounding the art market, truth in photography, censorship, the birth of video art, and feminism's place in the art world.
    - New York, NY; 2006-05-12 (Box 1, Videotape 26A)
      Mini-DV (26A), Digital .mov file
    - New York, NY; 2008-02-15 (Box 1, Videotape 26B)
      Mini-DV (26B), Digital .mov file
  - Moira Roth
    Moira Roth (b. 1933), English-born and American-based critic, art historian and writer of fictional plays, poems, and narratives is an expert on Marcel Duchamp. She has become increasingly interested in cross-cultural connections and has traveled extensively in Southeast Asia. She has written about women and performance art in California and is currently teaching at Mills College in Oakland, California.
    - San Francisco, CA; 2005-03-04 (Box 1, Videotape 27A-27B)
      Mini-DV (27A, 27B), Digital .mov files (2)
  - Elizabeth Sackler
    Elizabeth A. Sackler (b. 1948) is a public historian, arts activist, and American Indian advocate who has been for many years a key figure in arts education and philanthropy. She has served on the National Advisory Board of the National Museum of Women in the Arts as well as on the Board of the Brooklyn Museum and is the founder and president of the American Indian Ritual Object Reparation Foundation. She is currently President and CEO of the Arthur M. Sackler Foundation and the founding president of the Friends of the Freer and Sackler Galleries of the Smithsonian Institution in Washington, D.C. As President of the Elizabeth A. Sackler Foundation, Dr. Sackler is responsible for the gift of Judy Chicago's The Dinner Party to the Brooklyn Museum, where it is permanently installed in the Elizabeth A. Sackler Center for Feminist Art.
    The recipient of numerous awards for her service and patronage, Dr. Sackler is published in scholarly journals, book and magazines and lectures on a variety of topics, from ethics in the art market to gender and art.
    - Brooklyn, NY; 2007-02-06 (Box 1, Videotape 28A)
      Mini-DV (28A), Digital .mov file
  - Miriam Schapiro
    As with many of the artists associated with the feminist art movement, Miriam Schapiro (b. 1923) began her career surrounded by the male-dominated movements of the 1950s and 60s, particularly Abstract Expressionism and hard-edge painting. As she developed as an artist, she began to incorporate the structures and brushwork typical of these movements into a body of work that addressed the uniqueness of the female identity. For example, her OX series from the 1960s presents a set of very basic, abstract symbols of language that also combine to form a rather obvious stylized representation of the female vagina—a second layer of meaning that a viewer could deny but probably not ignore.
    Schapiro created her OX series after a move to Southern California—a life change that brought with it a faculty position at the California Institute of the Arts (CalArts), where she worked with Judy Chicago to establish the Feminist Art Program in 1971. Soon after, she and other members of the Program founded Womanhouse, and in 1972 Schapiro co-created the work Dollhouse, a piece that unapologetically integrated feminine imagery into the core of its meaning. During the 1970s Schapiro began to incorporate fabric into patchwork assemblages of paint, embroidery, and quilting that she called "femmages." These works were the starting point for her leadership in the postmodern, abstraction-focused Pattern and Decoration movement, a mode of art making that continued into the 1980s.
    - New York, NY; 1990-05-30 (Box 2, Videotape 30A-30B)
      U-matic (30A, 30B), Digital .mov files (2)
      Paper on Container
      Orange post-it stuck to face of container:
      "Problems w/ Master"
    - New York, NY; 1990-07-02 (Box 2, Videotape 30E)
      Betacam (30E)
      Manufacturer Information and sticker labels
    - Los Angeles, CA; 1992-09-03 (Box 2, Videotape 30 F)
      Hi-8 (30F), Digital .mov file
  - Miriam Schapiro and Faith Wilding
    - New York, NY; 1990-05-30 (Box 2, Videotape 30C-30D)
      U-matic (30C, 30D), Digital .mov files (2)
  - Carolee Schneemann
    A pioneer of feminist performance art, Carolee Schneemann, b. 1939, works in a wide variety of media including performance, assemblage, photography, film, video, and installation. Throughout her career, her work has found its loci in discourse on the body, sexuality, and gender. One of her most important early pieces was the multimedia performance work Meat Joy(1964) which incorporated nude dancers, contemporary popular music, raw meat, and sexual innuendo. From the same period came her first major film Fuses (1964-67), considered to be the first feminist erotic film. Banned and censored in several locales, it portrays the artist and her partner, James Tenney, in bed, watched by their cat, the images interspersed with landscape footage. Schneemann also burned, baked, cut and painted the film, creating layers of collage.
    Schneemann's flouting of convention was further defined by her later performance Interior Scroll (1975), in which she unrolled a text from her vagina and described the sexism and disdain women artists encounter in their careers from male colleagues and art critics.
    - Copenhagen, Denmark; 1990 (Box 2, Videotape 29A)
      U-matic (29A)
    - New York, NY; 1991-03-08 (Box 2, Videotape 29B-29D)
      U-matic (29B, 29C, 29D)
    - San Francisco, CA; 1991-10-05 (Box 2, Videotape 29E - 29F)
      U-matic (29E, 29F)
    - New York, NY; 2008-02-28
      The Carolee Schneemann interview starts at 00:04:04 and ends at 00:06:36 on the PS 1 digital file.
  - Lowery Stokes Sims
    Lowery Stokes Sims (b. 1949) is Curator at the Museum of Arts and Design in New York. From 2000-2007 she was president and curator of the Studio Museum in Harlem and from 1972-1999 was on the educational and curatorial staff of the Modern Art department at the Metropolitan Museum of Art. While at the Metropolitan, Sims curated over forty exhibitions, many reflecting an interest in African American and women artists. She has written extensively on African, Latino/a, Native and Asian American artists and taught art history, curatorship, and art criticism at Bard College and Queens College, among others. She is a noted specialist in the field of Euro-American African Art, with particular emphasis on the work of Wilfredo Lam. In addition to authoring numerous significant catalog essays for the Metropolitan, she has been a frequent contributor to such periodicals as Artforum and Arts Magazine.
    - New York, NY; 2006-05-12 (Box 1, Videotape 31A)
      DVCAM (31A)
  - Sylvia Sleigh
    Sylvia Sleigh (b.1916) moved to the United States from Wales in the 1960s. She is perhaps best known for her feminist parodies of iconic paintings which incorporate gender reversal in famous themes. Works that allude to well-known paintings by such masters as Giorgione, Titian and Manet—who all treated the theme of the reclining Venus—depict male rather than female nudes. Similarly, Sleigh replaced Ingres's nude women in Turkish bath scenes with bathing men. She used these works to explore the question of values attached to the traditional representations of women and men, and to draw attention to the absence in Western art of erotic portraits of men. In her many portraits of Paul Rosano, a model she painted many times in the 1970s, Sleigh satirically juxtaposed the idealized stances traditionally given to gods or figure-heads with commonplace contemporary settings.
    In a 2007 interview for Myartspace, Sylvia Sleigh was asked if gender equality issues in the mainstream art world, and the world in general, had changed for the better. Sleigh answered, "I do think things have improved for women in general; there are many more women in government, in law and corporate jobs, but it’s very difficult in the art world for women to find a gallery." One of her most well known paintings, A.I.R. Group Portrait (1977), depicts the members of a gallery (to which she herself belonged) that was founded to begin addressing this inequality.
    - New York, NY; 2008-02-28
      The Sylvia Sleigh interview begins at 00:24:08 and ends at 00:27:54 in the WACK! PS1 digital file.
  - Nancy Spero
    Nancy Spero (1926-2009) was a painter who, through her artwork and her direct political engagement, made sexism, racism, violence, and the abuse of power the main themes of her career. In the 1960s much of her work related to the Vietnam War; the War Series (1966-70) depicted rudimentary, phallic bombs and helicopters against plain white backgrounds. This technique, of drawing or painting isolated images on sheets of paper, sometimes with stamped typography and collage, became her signature. As, in the 1970s, she began to concentrate solely on the experiences and oppressive treatment of women, she developed a simplified vocabulary of forms: goddesses, gods, animals, monsters, and disembodied heads. Her work Torture in Chile (1974), for example, was a pale image of heads, geometric constructions, and snakes, hung below the printed words "Torture in Chile women reaching the Buen Pastor Jail have been subjected to the most brutal tortures live mice and insects introduced into vaginas hair pulled out by the handfuls nipples blown off or burnt genitals destroyed by electricity."
    Spero's political interests in the 1970s ran parallel to the subjects that she was exploring in her artwork. In 1969 she joined the Art Workers Coalition, an organization that worked to address iniquities in the art world and in society in general (one of its main causes being an end to the Vietnam War). She also became active in Women Artists in Revolution and, in 1972, co-founded Artists in Residence (A.I.R.) Gallery, a cooperative exhibition space in New York for women artists.
    Spero has received awards from the College Art Association, the Women's Caucus for Art, Skowhegan, and the American Academy of Arts and Letters. Her work has been exhibited at the Museum of Modern Art, Museu d'Art Contemporani de Barcelona, the Museum of Contemporary Art, Los Angeles, the MIT List Visual Arts Center, and the Institute of Contemporary Arts, London.
    - New York, NY; 2008-02-18
  - Marcia Tucker